Good morning! My name is Krzysztof Zakrzewski
and I had an opportunity to provide my voice in the 'History of Khroinis'
Gothic II: The History of Khorinis
Krzysztof Zakrzewski is a true legend in the world of polish cinema and dubbing.
A veteran of scenes in the biggest polish and warsaw theatres like Teatr Nowy, Ateneum or Komedia.
He provided a voice for the biggest productions of the studios such as DreamWorks, Disney and Pixar, in which he provided voice to 'Where is Nemo?'.
He provided voice for all the biggest computer roleplaying games - from Skyrim to Dragon Age.
In Gothic 3 he provided a voice of character named Tjalf - a leader of the Hammer Clan in Nordmar:
'The Orcs have captured our mine with the oven.
The pride of our clan lies in the hands of those hairy bastards.
Our ancestors would be rolling in their graves, if they knew about it.'
Besides, everyone should also remember his amazing portrayal as a dwarven banker Vivaldi in the Witcher 1:
'Right now the dwarves. A segregation from the first word...
How should I address you?
'You are like everyone else, like this damn city - Vizima. Everything for humans. Nothing for us.'
Also characters from the Witcher 2 and 3.
'Borzuj, who hunted for the heir, told that enough of that and he would go those beasts away.
'Oho.'
And also in the Bard's Tale.
'A barrel of malt, a bushel of hops, you stir it around with a stick'
'the kind of lubrication to make your engines tick'
Because of fact that he is in the top of the best polish voice actors, the cast of the 'History of Khorinis' couldn't be complete without him'
THE ROAD FROM THE WORLD OF CINEMA AND THEATRE TO DUBBING
I was a long time ago.
Of course for us the most important thing was theatre.
Nobody of us would have gone to play in movie
or in television, if he had had to abandon theatre
Theatre was the most important, and apart from theatre there wer other jobs.
One day I met with the late Madam Aleksandrowicz
and I went to her studio in order to make dubbing and then we started a long and growing cooperation.
Then, when we started work in dubbing,
a splice was on the loop
it walked in circles and it was tick, tick.... so it walked slowly once, second, third time...
Today it is done five or even ten times faster.
To this day I don't know how it is made.
I mean I am aware when is better or when is worse, when it could win.
Or could we win when we are looking for a temper of this character? Ok, but look for a temper in Captain Feathersword. It's difficult!
'A meeting in the middle of night? It's a scandal, Archmaster?
This damn Rigaldo has no shame!'
It was also funny moments that happened to me.
I was a witness of audition to the movie which was called 'Monsters Inc.'
Many friends of mine came, including children - girls.
and they were still looking or these old ladies didn't fit and kids resisted to do something... weird.
After the hearing I said incautiously that
'It must be a little child. I could bring my daughter here.'
So Joanna Wizmur - the director of polish dubbing in 'Monster Inc.' - said: 'You must be here with your child tomorrow.'
I came with my child, she is four years old and she is so 'stuffy', sick,
but she's got something in voice that is unbelievable.
With this blocked nose, with all of this,
Joasia put my daughter before the desk,
they had set the microphones, she said: 'Ok, let's start it!'.
'Ok, so let's go. Remember Weronika that you must say 'kotek'. Yes'.
But in a headphone she hears 'kitty'.
'Okey, let's start it!'
Kotek? No, 'kitty'
'But Weronika, you must say 'kotek'
But in headphone she hears 'kitty'.
'Good, good.'
'Kitty'
Jesus Christ! Joasia, who was known from coarse language, came and said:
'Look! Look goddamnit, what you have written here? K-O-T-E-K, ok? Kotek!"
I said - 'Joasia, she is four years old, but she can't read...'
And well - everything messed up. However, Joasia, who was a wonderful director, came to idea how to make without this 'kotek' in ear and and we did it!
Indeed this movie was brilliant made.
And the funniest thing - there's a new genre.
And the games appeared.
It was weird, because none of us had not an experience in dubbing the games.
When it comes to making voice-over to the games
we were in a way - a group of people who was in dubbing more often -
ready to this work.
And it went so fast.
Of course we had a many problems, but it was a beginning.
I was cast like in the cartoons - as soldiers, policemen, thieves. Those were the roles in which I portrayed very often.
'No complaints, but my destillery is not working. An alembic and a cauldron should be cleaned, beceuse they smell suspicious.
Your father have not been here for a long time.'
I wanted to say that in this project I portray a role of Bolc the distiller.
Such a drunkard, distiller
a character close to me.
I bring troubles not only for myselff, but also for people, who are close to me and for whole village,
but it is so funny.
I wish you to meet more often with the professional treatment of dubbing.
Thank you to all of you and I also thank you to boys, who make this work.
You are perfect, brilliant and I believe that you will do everything good.
Let's wish good dubbings, beautfiul portrayals and of course do it, beceause it is worth.
I greet every fan of Gothic game and addon the 'History of Khorinis'!
And may Innos watch over you always.
I'm saying goodbye to you. Farewell!
English subtitles: Bartosz ‘Kereth’ Biały based on polish subitles made by Szymon ‘Szmyk’ Żak